Finding Aid to Dyke TV records SSC.MS.00656
Sophia Smith Collection
Dyke TV records
1992-2007
Sophia Smith Collection
Dyke TV
SSC.MS.00656
105.25 linear feet (93 boxes)
6 items (5 CDs and 1 floppy disk) part of 2018-S-0043
Television production company; Lesbian business. Collection includes video tapes, raw footage, and DVD dubs for Dyke TV programs. The materials cover a wide range of topics, including but not limited to lesbians in sports, artists, gay pride, childhood and coming of age stories, political issues, gay and lesbian civil rights, sexuality, lesbian parenting, HIV/AIDS and other health issues, incest survivors, lesbian domestic violence, and women's rights. [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online. Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Accruals
Further additions to the collection were made on 2018 April 23 and 2018 July 17, under Accessions 2018-S-0026 and 2018-S-0043.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Dyke TV Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by producers Sally Sasso and Mary Patierno in 2009.
Additional Formats
Selected Dyke TV episodes and the complete show logs have been digitized and are available to view online.
Biographical / Historical
Dyke TV was created by Ana Maria Simo (playwright and co-founder of Lesbian Avengers), Linda Chapman (theater director and producer) and Mary Patierno (independent film and video maker). The first show aired in New York City, June 8, 1993. Dyke TV produced national documentary television programming, by and for lesbians, designed to empower and to enhance the visibility of diverse lesbian communities; it mixed art, news, sports, political commentary, health coverage, music, and video as it examined issues of lesbian culture. The program reached over 6.5 million households nationwide, and was screened at many national and international film and music festivals. The half-hour weekly cable television show featured a five-minute news segment covering issues relevant to lesbian lives from a lesbian perspective; an in-depth look at an issue of particular interest to the lesbian community, including such topics as the International Dyke March at Stonewall 25, the murder of Brandon Teena, Camp Sister Spirit under siege, lesbians in the military, domestic partnership, and state-wide ballot initiatives and other anti-lesbian and anti-gay activities of the Christian Right; and interviews with lesbian artists, showcasing their work. Dyke TV won a Hometown Video Festival Award in 1994.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies. Viewing copies of most final broadcast shows are available.
Related Materials
Additional Dyke TV materials were donated to the Lesbian Herstory Archives, Brooklyn, NY
Scope and Contents
The records contain show master tapes, editor's master tapes, raw footage, and DVD dubs for Dyke TV programs. The materials cover a wide range of topics, including but not limited to lesbians in sports, artists, gay pride, childhood and coming of age stories, political issues, gay and lesbian civil rights, sexuality, lesbian parenting, HIV/AIDS and other health issues, incest survivors, lesbian domestic violence, and women's rights.
Lesbian activists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Lesbians -- United States -- History; Lesbians -- United States -- Social life and customs; Documentary television programs; Gay rights -- United States; Chapman, Linda; Patierno, Mary; Sasso, Sally; Simo, Ana Maria; Audiotapes; clippings; Videotapes; Publicity; CDs; Floppy disks; Patierno, Mary; Sasso, Sally; Patierno, Mary; Sasso, Sally; Chapman, Linda; Simo, Ana Maria
- Dyke TV records addition, approximately 1995-2005; 2018-S-0026; Patierno, Mary; 12.25 linear feet (10 records cartons and three bags of moldy tapes)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Twenty-one moldy tapes removed from boxes 6, 7, and 10 and placed in in quarantine (3 bags) West St. Basement 195 C 3-4 (as boxes 6a, 7a, and 10a)
  Scope and Contents
  The records contain show master tapes, editor's master tapes, raw footage, and DVD dubs for Dyke TV programs. Also included are meeting notes, financial records, and fundraising materials. The materials cover a wide range of topics, including but not limited to lesbians in sports, artists, gay pride, childhood and coming of age stories, political issues, gay and lesbian civil rights, sexuality, lesbian parenting, HIV/AIDS and other health issues, incest survivors, lesbian domestic violence, and women's rights.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Donated by Mary Patierno, Dyke TV co-creator.
  Patierno, Mary
  - Board materials and meeting notes, foundational materials, production materials, and publicity, 1994-2004 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Staff meeting notes and minutes, staff retreats, 1995-2000 (Box 2)
  - Show logs, approximately 1995-2000 (Box 2)
  - Notes from starting Dyke TV, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Fundraising, fundraisers and events, including 10th anniversary gala, approximately 1994-2004 (Box 1, Box 2, Box 9)
  - Financial summaries and budgets, approximately 1994-2003 (Box 9)
  - Video recordings "Marlene Talks About March" and "Ursala's Facial Exercises and Advice", approximately 1993-2005; 2 items (2 U-matic video tapes) (Box 3)
    Videotapes
  - Video recordings "Eyewitness: Joan Nestle" and "Ani Di Franco," "Noemi Masliah Interview (Immigration Part 1)," "Boys Don't Cry," "Suddenly Not Susan," "Lesbians Talking Straight," "Peace Rally in D.C. (raw footage and interviews)," "Alice B. Toklas #2," and "Kiss the Girl", 1994-2001; 9 items (9 Betacam video tapes) (Box 3)
  - Video recordings "Doin' it til we're satisfied," "Harriet's workshop (?)," "Risk: Lesbians & AIDS," "Dyke TV: Avenge Tampa," and "On Our Backs", 1995; 5 items (5 Betacam video tapes) (Box 4)
  - Video recordings "Avengers, Part 1" & "Sapphic Spitcurls," "Cathy Opie" and Anita & Alexis," "Institute for the Musical Arts (IMA) June [Millington] footage," "June Millington & IMA", 1993-2001; 4 items (4 Betacam video tapes) (Box 4)
  - Video recordings "African American Lesbian Child," "Anne Northrop" & Pamela Sneed," "Lori E. Seid," "Titi Liberation," and "Hot Head Paisan", 1993-1995; 5 items (5 Umatic video tapes) (Box 4)
  - Video recordings "Interview with Meg Riley," "Pamela Sneed," "Dyke March," "Pope, Clinton, Colorado," "Toshi Reagan--Arts," Mary Ellen Strom: School's Out," "Glow," "Lesbian Country Western Dancing," "Tattoo Talk 2," "Gay Women's Focus: Health care for Lesbians," "Dyke Signs, #1, #2, #3", 1990-1998; 8 items (8 Umatic video tapes) (Box 5)
  - Video recordings "Cupake Drag King piece," "Entrevista," "Latinas War," "Dyke March Doin' it til..." "Queen Nelora and the Fantastic Courting Yard," "Toi, No Case, News, Julie Goldman, etc.", 1997-2004; 6 items (6 Betacam video tapes) (Box 5)
  - Dyke TV shows #178; 213-214; 228; 256-260; 268-271; 274-274; 276-278; 284-286; 317b; 318a; and 320b, Approximately 1995-2005; 23 items (23 shows) (Box 6)
  - Video recordings "Rumours," "Outloud," "Astraea," and "No on one Main", Approximately 1995-2005; 1 items (1 U-matic video tape) (Box 7)
  - Video recordings "Ann Northrop News," "Dia en BA," "Blah Blah 2," " and "Cris Williamson, Holly Near, Ann Meredith", 2001-2002; 4 items (4 Betacam SP video tapes, large format) (Box 7)
  - Video recordings "Dyke TV Highlights," "Dyke TV Sample Show," "Matt Shephard Stills," "Poorly Understood: Jen Taylor(Formerly Known as History Lesson #1)" [2 copies], 1999-2001; 5 items (5 BetaCam SP tapes, small format) (Box 7)
  - Video recordings "Beijing", 1995; 9 items (9 Betacam tapes in Box 8); 11 items (9 Betacam SP tapes and 2 Hi8 videocassettes in Box 10) (Box 8, Box 10)
  - Moldy video tapes, 21 items (21 video tapes) (Box 6a, Box 7a, Box 10a)
    21 moldy video tapes removed from boxes 6,7, and 10--put into quarantine as boxes 6a, 7a, and 10a, all in plastic bags in West St Basement 195 C 3 and 4.
- Dyke TV records further addition, 1990-2005; 2018-A-0043; Patierno, Mary; 3 linear feet (2 record cartons and 1 full letter document box); 7 boxes (7 moldy boxes; quarantined in bags until further assessment is possible and thus not inventoried.)
  Materials have been held by Mary Patierno, Dyke TV co-creator, since the time that Dyke TV was disbanded.
  Materials include video tapes of Dyke TV episodes and content, as well as photographs and slides of content and production. Also includes financial documents, incorporation information, job descriptions for various positions, advertisements, and programming.
  CDs in Box 2 and floppy disc in Box 3 have been flagged for digital archivist.
  Boxes with moldy contents were quarantined for further assessment and those not inventoried.
  - Video recording "Gender Expression PSA", April 2003; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recordings, "Footage for Night Life promo", approximately 1995-2005; 1 items (1 Maxell Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV 114: I'm You, You're Me", 1995 August 28; 1 items (1 3M video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV 173" including, "Lesbian Living: Kate Clinton," "Hanging out in the Bathtub - cartoonists," "Butch wax: Music Video," "Anna Ferrer - Visual Artist," "Cyndy Rickman: Music Video," and "I was a Lesbian Child", approximately 1997-1999; 1 items (1 SONY KSP-30 video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV show 181", 1999 January; 1 items (1 SONY KSP-30 video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recordings, "Dyke TV unmixed masters, shows 222-224", approximately 2000-2002; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV 236", approximately 2000-2002; 1 items (1 3M video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV 241", approximately 2000-2002; 1 items (1 SONY KCA-30BRS video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV show 266", approximately 2000-2002; 1 items (1 SONY KCA-30BRS video tape) (Box 1)
  - "Dyke TV 270", 2002 December 17; 1 items (1 SONY KSA-30BRST video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV Pride vision shows (masters), 277 and 278", approximately 2003-2005; 1 items (1 Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recordings, "Dyke TV unmixed masters, shows 284, 287, 288", approximately 2003-2005; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Dyke TV Pridevision masters, 285, 287, 288", approximately 2003-2005; 1 items (1 Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Master pridevision, 286, 289, 290", approximately 2003-2005; 1 items (1 Betacam SP video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recording "Episode ??" containing "Opening Trailer," "Brandon Teena," "I was a Lesbian Child," "Dyke Match," "Out in the Video Store," "Two Spirited People," "Flying," "risk: Lesbians and AIDS," "Margo Gomez," "Klexmatics," and "Lesbianism: What a Beautiful Choice", approximately 1995-2005; 1 items (1 3M video tape) (Box 1)
  - Video recordings, "GLAAD Awards", 2002; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recordings, "Alice B. Toklas #3", approximately 1995-2005; 1 items (1 Kodak U-Matic video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recordings, "Raw Word Project," "VAL intros incl: DC Rally, NYC Rally, The Farm, Jennifer Munson, etc.", 2001 Oct 1; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recordings, "Pills Profits and Protest," "Footage from Brazil", approximately 1995-2005; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recordings, "AIDS ride #1," "Anat Salomon", 1999; 1 items (1 SONY Betacam SP video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recordings, "Butch Beer Commercial", 1997 July; 1 items (1 Fujifilm D2 video tape) (Box 2)
  - Video recording "Compilation for the new festival", 1994; 1 items (1 SONY video tape) (Box 2)
  - Dyke TV advertisements and newspaper clippings, 1994-1995; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Dyke TV incorporation information and paperwork, 1990-1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Programming, sponsorship, production information, and production workshops, 1994-1996; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Employee, volunteer, intern, and board policies and job descriptions, 1994-2001; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
  - "Snapshots at Dyke TV" photographs, approximately 1995-1998 (Box 2)
  - "Snapshots at Dyke TV", approximately 1995-1998; 5 items (5 CDs); .430 Gigabytes (210 jpg image files) (Box 2)
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access.
  - Slides for Dyke TV stills, approximately 1995-2000; 2 Sheets (2 sheets of slides) (Box 3)
  - Financial information (fundraising, fiscal reports, budgets, and tax information), 1994-1999; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - Newsletters and mailings, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) Contains floppy disc (Box 3)
  - Newsletter vol 2., no. 1: images, graphics, 1995; 1 items (1 floppy disk); .236 Gigabytes (19 digital files) (Box 3)
    Note on file formats: contents consists of Mac desktop publishing software files from 1995 (Quark file format). Special Collections is not able to provide the required software or system specifications for this file format.